<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gorgon's head or The monster of Munster cloaked with a lamb's skinn</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1303A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829939</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829939</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34386</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34386)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2030:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gorgon's head or The monster of Munster cloaked with a lamb's skinn</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by and date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With a postscript.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Ireland --  Munster --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Munster (Ireland) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34386:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34386:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The GORGON'S HEAD or The Monſter of Munſter</head>
            <head type="sub">Choaked with a Lamb's Skinn</head>
            <p>OH <hi>Monſter:</hi> Oh <hi>Monſtrous Monſter:</hi> The <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Monſters:</hi> The <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of <hi>Munſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Woe to you <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> when the <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> appeares. He is a Wolf in Sheep's Clothing; He left NOT ONE <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> alive to tell their own ſtory: much leſs to contradict the Others ſo largely written in their Innocent Blood. In the Maſſacres of FRANCE and IRELAND they were not half ſo cunning: therefore they that eſcaped Lived to Record their Cruelty in Red Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But our <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> NOT Leaving ONE, made their own Relation Authentick. And lett all men Judge, whether <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> did not deſerve to be ſo ſerved; for all thoſe Deſpiſed things through-out, <hi>POLAND, H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NGARY, BO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMIA, GERMANY,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> (as all men and women who have been in thoſe Parts can wittneſs) inſtead of Deſtroying their Enemies or Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves, hold it a ſin to Reſiſt Evil, becauſe their Saviour forbids them: And think it fitt that if a man ſmite them on the one cheek, to turn t'other, And our own Relators tell us, that theſe <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> ſtood ſtill, and lett out <hi>Monſter</hi> kill them: and ſome of them climb'd up upon Trees wayting for Miraculous help from Heaven: but our Party prevented that Miracle. Oh that they would do ſo here in <hi>ENGLAND</hi> (cries the <hi>Rabble</hi>) then ſhould not our Pulpits and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets need to tell ſo many <hi>Lyes</hi> to Incenſe the Multitude; Nor ſhould we need to Diſarm and Disfranchize them from all <hi>Engliſh Liberties</hi> before we kill them. And when all is done, we are ſo diſmaied, that we know not how to go about it, for fear left when they are gone, we ſhould be no wayes able to Cope with our Numerous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34386:2"/>Enemies of the other hand. For our <hi>Miniſters</hi> are ſo zealous and inompatible ſince they were Infected with New <hi>ENGLAND</hi> ſpirits, and tryumphed over the Biſhops that we have not one friend left but our ſelves: and we are friends to none but our ſelves, But the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> heretofore have been our beſt and ſureſt friends, and ſtouteſt Warryers in time of Danger. And the GOD of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf ſo Partially for them, that we know not well how to be againſt them.</p>
            <p>Yet we have the <hi>Monſter</hi> on our ſide: and he is very bold and ſubtil: as ſubtil as the old Serpent. He hath lately crept up into our Pulpits, who in the beginning of theſe Warrs was hardly known amongſt us. And now tells us ſtories of half an hour long, which are held as true, and Orthodox as the Goſpel they preach. For we have heard with our own eares, and they have declared it openly in their Sermons, that the <hi>Monſter</hi> was come into <hi>England:</hi> and that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>England</hi> would have cut All our Engliſh Throats (and we had no other to eate ſweet meets and drink burnt Wine with a Chriſtnings.) And if they had Cut All our Throats, and our Miniſters too, none of us all could have terrified the vulgar with theſe lamentable ſtories. For we never heard of any that ſpake after their Throat was Cut. And many of us have been put into grievous frights by it: ſo that we felt on our Throats to find whether it were not done already: but we found them yet very ſound and whole, which is a certain and infallible demonſtration that our Monſter is a Prophet, and foretells things before they come to paſs, or likely to come to paſs. For we are yet all living, and mean to Cut theirs: Ah Rogues Cut our Throats? we'l be revenged on them. A ſilly Waterman the other dy boaſted how many <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Throats he would Cut for his ſhare: and ſhould we be behind a ſilly Waterman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n our Zeal for the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> For we ſay this is the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> what ever they affirm to the contrary. It was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in <hi>Neroes</hi> time, and all the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors time: It was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in all the ten Perſecutions: It was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in the Maſſacre of <hi>France.</hi> I was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Germany:</hi> It was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in Qeene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes: And it was lately the <hi>Good Gld Cauſe</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and ſhould have been the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> throughout all <hi>Germanay.</hi> What ſhould we looſe time? It is and hath been the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in all times and places, from the beginning of the World to this day, to Cut the Throats of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks though they were not all Anabaptiſts, and ſo will continue to the end of the World, if the zealous Orthodox men of the times might have but their own will, <hi>Abel</hi> was an Heretick, who being neither Prieſt nor Levite, but a younger brother, would offer and preferr the ſtrong ſavovr of a Lamb, before the ſweet ſmell of the Fruits and Hearbs of his Elder Brother, but it coſt him his life; And <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth himſelf to be accounted an <hi>Hereteck</hi> amongſt the Orthodox Scribes and Phariſees of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34386:2"/>his time, when he was accuſed by thoſe learned men (the <hi>Children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi>) to be a ringleader of the Sect of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and by that meanes a Peſtilent fellow and mover of ſedition (<hi>Act.</hi> 24.5.14.) A <hi>Sect</hi> that was every where ſpoken againſt, (<hi>Act.</hi> 28.2.) And theſe men, who were Jews, the very Children of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> to whom pertaind the <hi>Adoption</hi> and the <hi>Glory,</hi> and the COVENANTS, and the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the SERVICE of GOD, and the PROMISES, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 5. Theſe men cryed out away with him from the Earth, it is not fit ſuch a fellow ſhould live (<hi>Act.</hi> 21, 22. &amp; 25, 24.) Yet he was but one, and ſhould we ſuffer ſuch a numberleſſe number of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to live, who are ſo many? who we? who are the Children of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and whoſe Children are in the <hi>Covenant?</hi> what we? who are indeed ſuch very Children of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that we know not the right from the left, nor the old from the new in matter of Covenant? And that is the reaſon (by the way) that we do break our Covenant ſo often, and act things ſo directly contrary to our Holy League and <hi>Covenant:</hi> But that's a trifile, that's but by the by, as we ſaid, and now quite out of date, let us now return to our Monſter again, and hear his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies. For we may well call him a Prophet that tells things (like the welſh Prophet <hi>Arize Evans</hi> of <hi>Black-friers</hi>) before they are, or will be, or like to be: yea, perhaps ſuch notable things as are impoſſible ever to be: therefore how tranſcendent a Prophet is he? ſhould not ſuch be beleived? what not ſuch as our very Godly Miniſters themſelves beleive, without ſo much as examinings the probability of the thing? And they themſelves preach it as matter of Faith to be beleived: For if they would not have us beleive it, why ſhould they preach it? and that at the very ſame time when they preach unto us their Goſpel; yea at our moſt ſolemn meetings of all? In times of Feaſting, and times of Faſting, and greateſt humiliation and ſincerity before Almighty God. It oft doth ſerve their turn inſtead of the Goſpel it ſelf, ſo as to furniſh them with the greateſt part of their Sermon. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is of farr greater uſe to them then the beſt Text of Scriptures, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing the Anabaptiſts. For when we or our Miniſters have nothing at all to ſay for our ſelves againſt the Anabaptiſts, we do but raiſe up this Monſter, and ſo ſtops the mouths of the common people, who elſe would be all running af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them; But when they ſee this Monſter in the way, they come running back to us again for ſhelter: as we ſee little Children ſcared with a Bulbeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And it is a plain CASE that our CALAMITY were very great if we had not this Monſter for our refuge at a dead lift. And ſurely the ſtory cannot but be true and concerns us very much to be ſo. We muſt, we will,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34386:3"/>we cannot but beleive it. For whom ſhould we beleive if we beleive not our Godly Miniſters? 'Tis true, we are yet alive: elſe how could it well be a Propheſie? And both we and they muſt tell theſe things whilſt we are alive, for when we are dead we ſhall not ſpeak one word: and ſo our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be repreſented, as fowl as the Anabaptiſts themſelves, who never ſpake one word ſince they were killed: But now we may ſay what we will for all them. The men of <hi>Munſter</hi> alſo that killed the Anabaptiſts told their ſtory whilſt they themſelves were alive: but they were no Prophets as we read of: but plain Hiſtorians writing of things paſt; yet farr more ſubtill then common Hiſtorians, who can relate no further then every man may have ſeen or heard: but theſe declare the very ſecret purpoſe and intentions of the Anabaptiſts, which lay ſo ſecret within them, that perhaps the ſilly Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts themſelves never knew it, nor no man elſe till the men of <hi>Munſter,</hi> who killed them, and opened them, and ſaw their very hearts, revealed it to the world, as the true and juſt reaſon of their ſo dealing with them: leſt any man ſhould judge them cruel to do ſo horrid an Act without cauſe, and ſo abhorr both them and their Religion for ſo doing, as ſome have done the moſt devout and learned <hi>Calvin,</hi> for cauſing <hi>Michael Servetus,</hi> who fled our of <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Geneva</hi> for Conſcience ſake, and was there burned for not mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting preſently into all Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> Orthodox Opinions, and ſo was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the fire, ſuppoſing him to be like wax, and being heated, the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for their purpoſe: but he proved combuſtible to aſhes. We have ſeen therefore wherein their zeal failed, and hope to make better uſe of ours. We are all forewarned from the firſt time that Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> had the watchword, and though he miſcarried, yet we (by Presbyteriean Providence) are once more forearmed: And what ſhould we do with our Armes, if not to cut the Anabaptiſts and all Sectarian Throats? For when we have cut all their Throats, we ſhall be then ſure they cannot cut ours. We have the Sword, and ſhould we weare it in vaine, as the Anabaptiſts did? For they did not ſo much as touch the hair of our heads all the while they had the power in their hands, and would you have us to do ſo to? They knew not what to do with the Sword, but we do, and they ſhall know it to their Coſt. We have already turned out 400 of their Officers, and diſarmed the reſt to expoſe them to the incenſed mercy of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who have already begun to burn and ſpoyl ſome of their Goods and Houſes, to the value of 500 l. for one man, and threaten the like to the reſt; That the Presbyterean Plot might in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be undervalued, or give place to the Traytor <hi>Strafford's:</hi> whoſe deſigne was the forerunner of that Glorious <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacre ſo highly Canonized in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34386:3"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and amongſt all zealous Catholicks. And ſome are clapt up, for fear leſt being provoked they ſhould ſerve us the ſame ſauce, for they are much for <hi>DO</hi> as you would be <hi>DONE</hi> by, an old obſolete Law of the Jewes and the old Chriſtians above 1600 yeares ago, as if it were a better Law then all the Lavves of our Native Country. A Company of Lavvleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they are; They vvould have all things done by Love (for-ſooth) if they might rule the roſt; And ſo all our Auncient Fundamentall Lawes would down at once. But we hope our Lawyers will ſee to that: For if they go down, it is their fault more then ours: for they are choſen Speakers, and they are chofen Chaire men, and they are choſen Secretaries, and they are choſen Judges, and they are choſen Ambaſſadors, and they are choſen Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates, Serjeants and Counſellers. Yet we ſhould not much ſtand upon it, if they were all down, ſo our Godly Miniſters were up, and not one whit abridged of their Tythes and Argmentations, and all impropriations and Gleab Lands and daily freewill offerings, firſt fruits and tenth of Tythes and the like. Poor Miniſters! They have had a hard pull on't; They were fain to be entertained at the chiefeſt Tables in all the Land, and had like to have loſt Livings of 400 ot 500 l. a year, and ſome divers Livings and places to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the value of one thouſand or fifteen hundred pounds a year. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many of them could not Preach all the while; yea they were fain to turn their preaching into ſoliciting and pleading: But we have now gotten the Parliament trump on our ſide, and we care not a pin for the Anabaptiſts, if they ſtick faſt to us. And now if <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> would but come in upon our Termes and Confirme, all that we do, we ſhould carry the Game be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; And if he ſhould not, we would deal with him in the ſtool of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and if that would not ſerve turn, we could make him as Glorious a King as we did his Father, and have another Free Parliament into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; And our Godly Miniſters would take care enough in all places that no Sectaries ſhould be choſen; for we could ſooner comply with <hi>Papiſts</hi> then with them. Yet if <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> ſhould bring with him the 200000 <hi>Scotteſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who have been baniſhed, and ſuffered with him all this while: beſides all the Rabble of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and all the Engliſh alſo beyond Sea, to joyn with the Malignants and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (whoſe Lands we have gotten into our poſſeſſions) and make us live again like Peſants and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, and poor Sneaks, who now live like Lords, yea and ſome of us d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bd Lords, both by the mighty Protector, and the Almighty and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Rump (as we call them when we are by our ſelves, or amongſt the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants): For the Truth is we dare not well truſt them, for all their colloging with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34386:4"/>our Miniſters and Inns of Court, in eſtabliſhing our incomparable Lawes, and the Auntient Divine Right of Tythhs, and Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in an other Title; we had rather have thoſe of 48, or a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for we dare not truſt theſe further then we can throw a Millſtone; nor had done ſo much as we do, but that they put the Sword into our friends hands; In whom we put far greater confidence then in them; And yet it ſticks in our Stomack to think of <hi>C. S.</hi> whether he have any more <hi>Irelands</hi> and Biſhops, Deanes, and Chapters Lands to give us. And if he ſhould be too cunning for us, we ſhould wiſh the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> alive again to help us. And yet now it is aqueſtion, whether they would not ſooner joyn with him, being promiſed better Conditions, and ſurer Tolleration then ever we are like to afford them. Really (and that was the Old Protectors ſober Oath, when he did not ſwear in private) Really it is a hard CASE and CALAMITY we are put too, whether we ſhould let them live or no? We muſt adviſe with our Miniſters, they are Wiſer then we. What ſhould we doubt? They tell us all things that ſhall come to paſs in another World, and cannot they tell what will come to paſs here? we truſt them in greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we may well truſt them for the leſs; For if it were not for them, we ſhould be as ignorant as Papiſts. And yet we ſee what an excellent order they keep by beleiving as the Church beleives, and if we ſhould not do ſo to, we ſhould ſoon come to Confuſion. It is a dangerous thing to know too much, for <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that thereby ſorrowes are increaſed. Therefore we ſee the <hi>Papiſts</hi> putting all that trouble upon their Prſeſts, and they upon the Pope, they go on as boldly and reſolutely, and couragio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly as blind Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: and ſurely in many things the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will ſhame us; for they beleive what their Prieſts ſay, before they beleive their own eyes, or their own taſt, or their own hands. And we know that our Godly Miniſters are a great deal more learned then they: For they ſay ſo themſelves. And in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, if they meet with a Popiſh Ceremony in the way, they will ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas it, confute it, and be ſo learned upon it, that none in all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have one word to ſay againſt them, or if they had the very Reverence of the man and his Office (together with the ſevere Laws, and that Statutes of the Land) do ſo over-aw them, that they all depart in peace.</p>
            <p>And by this meanes he that is moſt in the Miniſters favour, is moſt in the favour of the whole Pariſh, and hath moſt reſpect. And it is the only way of Preferment in the Commonwealth; therefore we are reſolved to ſtick by our Miniſters, whether right or wrong. It is a plain CASE that CALA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITY attends all thoſe that ſide not with them, and they are nigh to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtruction,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34386:4"/>What wiſe man therefore will ſide with the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> we look upon them as our deadly and mortall Enemies, and ſo intend to prove them. If they can but hanſomely proceed (as they have begun) in <hi>Ireland;</hi> we will prove them both Mortall and deadly, if Fire and Fagot, Halter and Gibbot can prevaile; It being a farr eaſier and ſafer way to proceed with them, and make them mortall one by one: then to deal with the leaſt Company of them together, leſt 10 of them ſhould chaſe 100. and 100 a 1000, as they ſay is written in the Scriptures, Oh they are a dangerous Generation. For we neither dare fight with them, nor ſpeak with them; For our Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they come to parly with them, cannot anſwer one of a thouſand. They will ſo thunder out Arguments, and Scripture after Scripture, that a man hath not a breathing time between. And if they were not more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly obedient to Magiſtrates then we are our ſelves, and that our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are ſo diligent night and day, early and late, by their Wives and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſolicit all the chief Magiſtrates againſt them, whilſt we nettle their Conſcience by crying out in all places that they will endure no Magiſtracy, becauſe they themſelves are not ambitious to be Magiſtrates: the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be ſoon over-run with the Doctrine of Baptiſmes; Not the Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible Baptiſm of Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> and the quakers, but the outvvard Waſhing of vvater vvith the inward Anſwer of a good Conſcience in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And in all theſe things we have found the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſo cunning and ſubtill, that when our Godly Miniſters have brought Scriptures which we before lookt upon as impregnable and invincible, they have taken thoſe very Scripturs and turned them upon our Miniſters, that they had not one word to ſay: But to flie off to other Arguments or end in a Huddle, or get behind the Covenant, and there they skip from one Covenant to another, ſomtimes in the Old, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the New, ſomtimes in both, ſomtimes in neither; and ſo get into a Thicket, they eſcape &amp; run away; ſometimes they ply it ſo Home that they make many of us believe that Jeſus Chriſt &amp; all his Apoſtles, and all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches for 300 years were all <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> And tell us that if Jeſus Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles were in our dayes, we ſhould even uſe them as the Jewes did: being the caſe is the ſame. For they all Dipped in Jordan and Aenon, and the River of <hi>Philippi &amp;c:</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt was but the Son of a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters Wife, And his Apoſtles but Fiſher-men, and were never Ordained by the Prieſts and Levites, nor of the Doctors; nor yet brought up in any Univerſities, Nor yet among the Learned, Except it were <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34386:5"/>yet they drew multitudes after them, &amp; went into Synagoges and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, Diſputed, Baptized, what not?</p>
            <p>Away with ſuch Dangerous Fellowes, a man cannot hear them but his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience is troubled for ever after, if he do not follow their wayes; And there is no way to reſiſt them but to feare the Conſcience with the Red Hot Iron of Obſtinacy and Reſolution; They are more Dangerous and powerfull then Inchanters, Conjurors, or Jeſuits; for the Jeſuits do uſe Inchantments and Conjurations, and have the Aſſiſtance of Magiſtrates and the Inquiſition, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the Scriptures, and have to help them aboundance of Wealth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Riches, yet if theſe <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were once countenanced, they would gaine 10 Proſelits for one of the Jeſuits, or of our Godly Presbiterian Miniſters either; And the very quakers have noway to eſcape them but to get into a dark Lanthorn, &amp; ſlie from the Scriptures to the Light within them. Down with them all, Downwith them; Let not one Live, for a litle Leaven Leavens a whole Lump: Ifone of them Live they will preſently Swarm into a Multitude. No way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with them but as with the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Root and Branch. Yet the Reviving of our Lawes and our Knack of old Tythes, with the Presbyterian &amp;c: (as well as the <hi>Biſhops</hi>) will inſenſible undermine them, and Conſume them, &amp; drive them into Lurking holes, and to flie to their Old Denn of Amſterdam, and Germany; Well fare New England; It is as Rare to ſee an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> amongſt them as a Wof in Old England; except it be in Sheeps Clothing, and of them are many thouſands.</p>
            <p>Well we are reſolved either they ſhall fall, or we will fall, Power indures no parity: ſhould we beat the Buſh, and another catch the Bird; Was it not we that ſtirred up all theſe Commotions; did not we ſtir up the Saylers and the Souldiers at firſt? did not we curſe <hi>Meroz?</hi> did not we bring in our Brethren of <hi>Scotland?</hi> did not we pull down the <hi>KING</hi> and Houſe of Lords and cut off their Heads? Did not we firk out the Biſhops, root and Branch, and got into their fatt Livings? did not we chuſe Parliament men, and fill'd up all Offices, and ſuffered only a few <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to help, and they think now to rule the Roſt, becauſe old <hi>Oliver</hi> proved too ſubtle for us? No ſuch matter? <hi>Oliver</hi> is now dead; Therefore they may ſee how they are deceived. Have not we yet a Sir <hi>George</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> a Sir <hi>Charles</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all our friends in <hi>Scotland:</hi> beſides our wiſe and ſubtle Pentionaries in Councills and elſewhere? Have not vve all the Apprentices on our ſide ſtill? And at a dead lift we have a <hi>C. S.</hi> upon any termes. But what have we fought for, if it be not for Liberty of Conſcience; And how can we poſſibly have Liberty of Conſcience, and the Sectaries have it alſo?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34386:5"/>As if Liberty of Conſcience were a two handed Lawyer, and could play Jack on both ſides. No; Liberty of Conſcience is on our ſide; We fought for it, and we will keep it ſafe enough from their comming to it. For we hope to be keepers of the very Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and it muſt be a large Conſcience that can hold all the Liberties of <hi>England;</hi> It is our Liberty of Conſcience to be uppermoſt, ſince Biſhops are down, who kept us from it. And ſince we came to the tickliſh point of Government, we have had a very tender Confcience, and diligent care that none ſhould have the like Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with us, leſt we ſhould not have liberty enough for our ſelves, and leſt they ſhould return to the Fleſh Pots of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> or elſe run into any Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we hold Erronious, ſo that we have concluded all others to be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and in State of Damnation. For how can we love others better then our ſelves? And whether we are right or wrong, All men ought to Beleive as we Belcive, and Do as we Do: For our Salvation lies at ſtake for it. And what benefit will it be to us that others ſhould be ſaved, if we be not? And if we ſhould not be ſaved, (who do all as our Miniſters bids us,) vvhat vvill become of thoſe that never come to our Sermons, nor care for vvhat our God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters Preach, ſave in matter of Faith and Repentance? And of ſuch the vvorſt vve meet vvith are the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for vve can outreaſon the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, Lutheran</hi> and <hi>quaker,</hi> and make them ridiculous: but the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> vvill outreaſon us, as if vve vvere almoſt as much to be condemned as they. And againſt them vve have no refuge but to flie to our Victorious and Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant <hi>Monſter.</hi> Go on therefore thou <hi>Monſter</hi> Perſecution; Not novv the <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> but the <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Si. <hi>George</hi> on Horſeback; who beſtrideſt and boaſteſt thy ſelf over <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And if thou meaneſt as thou ſayeſt, and the purpoſe of God be that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be thoſe fellovv Servants and Brethren that ſhould be killed as the Souls under the Alter vvere, <hi>Rve.</hi> 6.11. (For the vvord of God and the Teſtimony of Jeſus:) Then Satiat thy Cruel Mavv vvith Blood, or be blood-thirſty ſtill and never ſatisfied: And vvhat thou doeſt, do quickly; For the time is comming, and novv is, that though Judgment may begin at the Houſe of God: yet the dreggs ſhall be given to thee O <hi>Monſter.</hi> For it is vvritten, Wo to thee that ſpoileſt, and thou vvert not ſpoyled: And dealeſt Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and they dealt not Treacherouſly with thee: when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoil, thou ſhalt be ſpoyled; and when thou ſhalt make an end todeal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly, they ſhall deal Treacherouſly with thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.1. For God hath determined to render unto thee double, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. Here is the Patience of the Saints, and here are they that keep the Commandments of God and the Faith of Jeſus. Bleſsed are they that die in the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14, 12, 13. <hi>To God only wiſe be Glory, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34386:6"/>
            <head>The ſerious Poſcript.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> THat it is trve that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> (ſo called) were all of them Slain, Killed, Murthered, or Maſſacrd, is Confeſſed by all of that Party that were guilty or Abbettors in that Act, and relate the Story.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That none of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> that were ſo killed (for the Relators themſelves ſay none eſcaped) did ever anſwer for themſelves is out of queſtion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> That to Condemne one Party before the other be heard, the very Heathen accounted it Injuſtice and a Crime.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> That Parties will ſpeak <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruths to juſtifie themſelves, is a practice in all Countries: and we have too ſad experience of it in <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> That none of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in all <hi>Poland, Hungary, Germany, Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> or the Low Countrys will ſo much as fight or defend themſelves, or exerciſe any Magiſtracy, is a Truth known to all Merchants and Travellers that ever were in thoſe parts amongſt them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> That none of thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland, &amp;c:</hi> have any ſuch unjuſt, fooliſh, or rediculous Principles as are mentioned in that ſtory of <hi>Munſter</hi> is and hath been publickly proteſted againſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> That the Story of <hi>Munſter</hi> (as they relate it) ſeems to all ſober men a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, like <hi>Don quitote &amp; Sanca Panca.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> That if <hi>Knipperdoling Becol,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> were ſuch fellows, it can be no more wonder'd at then the Actings of <hi>Theaurau John Tauny,</hi> or Sir <hi>Thomas Parfons,</hi> (our late Knight of the Son) and yet the Court and City were not accuſed for their Extravagancies; And who can tell what Oppreſſion might force the rude multitude to in <hi>Munſter,</hi> as that of <hi>Maſſagnello</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> which might afterwards be laid upon the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> As all things whatſoever which ſavours of Folly or Cruelty, is at this day laid to the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe to the <hi>quakers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> That if <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden Knipperdoling</hi> or <hi>Becol</hi> had been <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and had plaid ſuch pranks. It is as unjuſt to charge all <hi>Auabaptiſts</hi> with it, as to charge all mankind with folly and madneſs, becauſe the men of <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and the dull Houſen in <hi>Holland,:</hi> are ſo; Or becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> was an Apoſtle to charge all the Apoſtles with Treaſon, or as if one <hi>Presbiterian</hi> were Executed for Rapes and Murther, all <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſhould be charged guilty of the like ſinnes.</item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34386:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> But that all Sober People may know what to think of <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> They may be pleaſed to know.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> That their only Generall Rule to walk by is the Scripture of the Old and New Teſtament as they agree together. According to which Rule in particular, firſt, They ought to Suffer Wrong rather then do any.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, As to Magiſtrates. They beleive themſelves bound by the Doctrin and Example of Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, <hi>Mat. 17.27. Mat. 22.21. Rom. 13, 14. to 8. &amp; 1. Pet. 2.13, 14.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, If any do otherwiſe they dare not allow it in themſelves, much leſs in others.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, If any have been miſtaken in theſe changeable and miſtaken Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities: when every one that got hold on the Hilt, was proclaimed Maſter of the Sword: And all Authorities bowed thereunto: Miſtaken Obedience could not properly be a Sin of Wilfullneſs or Preſumption.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Judge not, that ye be not Judged,</hi>
                  <bibl>Mat. 7.1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
